Hello, welcome this is short training 1.3
this video introduces basics about
safety assurance cases using GSN notation
let's introduce some general concepts about assurance cases,
introduce the GSN notation, and show an example of a safety assurance case
an Assurance Cas represents a reasoned and compelling argument
that a service. system or organization will operate
as intended for a given application in a given environment
in other words, the assurance case makes a solid argument based on evidence
that the system operates and complies with requirements specifications
safety assurance cases, in particular, focus on demonstrating
that a given system is acceptably safe to operate in a given context
arguments are structured as a series of claims,
that state an overall claim
e.g. in the design of a critical system, the main claim is that the system
is acceptably safe to operate
the claims are refined into supporting claims,
and these supporting claims provide rationales to explain requirements and design decisions
examples of claims are requirements, hazards, design definitions,
i.e., any aspect of the system design that needs to be adequately satisfied or mitigated
at some point in the argumentation, the claims are not further refined,
and are then linked to pieces of evidence that support the claims
the set of evidence is formed by artifacts produced throughout the development process
the GSN (Goal Structuring Notation) is a
visual notation for building the arguments of assurance cases
by using GSN, it is possible to explicitly document the entire hierarchy of
claims and evidence that structure the argument in favor of a system
the notation provides a semantics for constructing arguments,
claims are called "Goals", supporting arguments can be "Strategies",
"Assumption" or "Justifications", and items of evidence are
ultimately "Solutions", contextual information is mapped to elements of type "Context"
the GSN main elements follow the visual notation depicted on the left
in the figure on the right, there is a partial example of a assurance case
"Goals" represent something to be achieved, for example a requirement
to be satisfactorily implemented, or a hazard to be adequately mitigated
the "Goals" comprise the central structure of the argumentation
"Strategies" represent explanations that clarify
how the high-level goal connects to supporting goals
for example in the figure, the strategy for dealing with hazard analysis is
to argue separately about product and process aspects
throughout the argumentation, it may be necessary to contextualize information,
the "Context" element is used to represent this
in the example in the figure, a requirements specification is used as "Context"
finally, in the bottom of the argument it is expected to have items of evidence, called "Solutions",
these solutions point to artifacts generated during the development of the system,
if an Goal is not refined into other Goals or linked to Solutions, we say that the
Goal is undeveloped, which is expected in the early phases of the project life cycle,
the GSN notation also defines two types of elements to
represent rationales: the "Justifications" and the "Assumptions"
the links allowed between GSN elements
are the link "Supported By" and the link "In Context Of"
in the previous slide, it is demonstrated the use of the "supported by" link that interconnects goals,
whereas the "in context of" link serves to associate
the main arguments to contextual or rationale information such as justifications and assumptions
let's present an example of a assurance case specified in GSN, which is based
in the same design model from the illustrative example of training 1.1
the design refers to a patient-controlled analgesic infusion pump, the part
of the design that we deal with in this example involves mitigating the hazard of battery exhaustion
the figure shows the modeling based on the SAIM model (Safety Assurance Information
Model) that we discussed in the previous training 1.1
Let's show how this information can be organized into an argument using GSN
the arguments are built based on the design information, in this part of the argument
the focus is on the hazard of battery exhaustion
the mitigation of this hazard is mapped as a high-level goal in the argument
note: throughout this example, we are highlighting the SAIM model excerpt on the left
and on the right how the element is mapped into the GSN argument
the argument then starts with a high-level hazard that was selected: battery exhaustion
in order to contextualize the hazard category to which this "battery exhaustion" belongs,
we mapped the high-level under-infusion hazard as a "Context" element
Continuing in the argument development,
the requirement "caregiver notification" mitigates the hazard of battery drain,
so the requirement is mapped as a Goal
and a "supported by" link is created between hazard and requirement
in turn, the assumption "Sufficient time", that provides an explanation for the
notification requirement, is mapped as a assumption and connected through the link "In Context Of"
the allocation of the requirement is also an important contextual information,
so the notification module is mapped as a "Context" element
advancing in the decomposition of the system, there is an "exhaustion notification" requirement that refines the
"caregiver notification" requirement. It is mapped as a "Goal" and linked by a "Supported By"
finally, the two sources that document the "exhaustion notification" requirement are
mapped as "Solutions", thus representing supporting evidence to the argument
it is important to emphasize that this is one of the valid alternatives for mapping
the design of this project to an argument in GSN, but it is not the only one
the mitigation of the hazard can be argued from
other perspectives, since there are a variety of argumentation patterns
what it is important to grasp is that, whatever the pattern of argumentation,
the information used is the same and originates in the project development artifacts
we completed this short training aimed to leverage some concepts about assurance cases
they are built based on project information, also requiring
information on rationales and safety assurance
there is no direct mapping of
project data to GSN elements, as the same project items can be mapped
differently depending on the argumentation pattern adopted
Thank you for your attention