Hello, welcome to the short training 2.1!
Let's introduce the ARCADE Framework
The main purpose of the Arcade Framework is the integrated management of safety assurance information together with regular project development information.
The image illustrates the Framework application context, where project and safety analysis teams use the same project management tools to store and retrieve information of the development lifecycle of a system.
safety analysis teams, in particular, need to produce artifacts for certification, such as safety assurance cases.
This task can be complex if the project data does not conform to a defined underlying information metamodel or when data related to safety assurance is disconnected from regular project data.
the ARCADE Framework provides support for the development process and preparation for certification.
It promotes integrated management of safety assurance data using common project tools, such as the Issue Tracking Systems or Application Lifecycle Management tools.
ARCADE supports the automated extraction of project data to perform a variety of analyses, so that we could integrate it easily into a development pipeline.
ARCADE also performs data consistency analysis according to the Safety Assurance Information Model along with other rules implemented in the internal ontology.
Knowledge discovery is supported by generating reports to classify and cross-reference explicit and implicit information extracted from management tools.
We call "implicit" information those which are inferred from the explicit information extracted from tools.
this contributes to a better knowledge discovery within the project's repository.
Finally, ARCADE automatically generates fragments of safety assurance cases based on a series of argumentation patterns.
the goal is to provide safety teams with multiple perspectives over the same data without the need to manually built different safety assurance cases in a visual modeling tool.
the scenarios of use that ARCADE helps to automate are:
reviewing project and assurance information,
exploring this information with a focus on knowledge discovery,
and producing safety assurance case reports for a project by re-using the automatically generated fragments.
the workflow starts with the extraction of information from project management tools.
In this version of the framework, it's connected to a Jira instance that contains issues, fields within those issues, and links between them.
Issue data is extracted by ARCADE and fed into an internal model based on the schema of the Safety Assurance Information Model.
this internal model is loaded into the ARCADE's internal ontology, which performs the following actions:
data consistency verification: explanations are computed to highlight the items with deviations and rules which were violated.
if the data is consistent, implicit classifications are inferred and fed back into the ontology, thus leaving the internal model with a mix of provided and inferred data.
on top of this combined data, queries are performed to retrieve information according to a set of competence questions implemented in the framework.
later on this video, some of these questions implemented in ARCADE will be shown.
"competence question" is a term from the ontology domain and represents a relevant question that a knowledge-based system needs to respond to users.
in ARCADE, the competence questions were devise to support the work of the development and safety teams, focusing on extracting information about the project's traceability.
On top of the same combined data, it's carried out some queries to construct arguments in GSN notation.
The term "fragment" denotes that arguments generated are not complete assurance cases reports, but rather a partial view that follows a pattern of argumentation from the literature.
in this video we'll present an ARCADE version deployed at a web address, which connects with a project management tool that we chose for initial integration.
this Atlassian Jira was customized to adopt the Safety Assurance Information model as shown on training 1.2
This is the main screen of the ARCADE tool, there are some pages with more detailed information about how the framework operates, how to adapt it for use, and a breakdown of the features and design decisions related to its development.
The tool starts with loading the ontology specification, which contains the rules and axioms verified by ARCADE.
It has this specification preloaded already.
the specification can be seen in these links at the beginning of this page.
if you want to reset the ontology, just click on "Reset" and the ontology is reloaded in the system.
the project data extraction is available for three projects hosted in the Jira instance.
the Open PCA project has already been explored in some other videos and in this part we are going to explore the DRONE project.
To load a project, ARCADE connects to the issue tracking system through the external access API and retrieves project data in proprietary format defined by Jira
this data is transformed to the internal model and then fed into the internal ontology
Let's load Open PCA Project data directly from Jira.
this may take a few seconds, because after transferring and transforming the data, ARCADE triggers consistency analysis routines, classification of information and generation of safety assurance cases.
if the data loading has no problems, a success message is shown.
some technical data is shown in the "details" section.
the number of items that were recovered, including number of issues, components and custom fields.
anything that is an element of the model, for example, assumptions and justifications, number of relationships between items, and quantity of related attributes.
regarding the inferred data, the details show new inferred classifications for items and new inferred relationships.
Let's show ARCADE's knowledge discovery using the Open PCA project.
the Jira project was automatically loaded with 94 objects from the Safety Assurance Information Model
these objects comprise issues, components and custom fields.
for example, issue OPEN PCA 71 is registered in Jira as a "Story" and was then mapped as a "Requirement".
some fields were extracted to fill the attributes of model:
name, description, status, creation date, update date and a URL in case you want to access the same issue in the original tool.
some elements of the model, which were mapped as custom fields in Jira, are imported as separate objects, such as assumptions and justifications.
and, finally, relationships with other issues were also extracted.
in the example show, the requirement is refined by three other requirements.
This view differs from the view provided by the Jira as the semantics of the model were applied.
Another example is "Component 10026".
"Component 10026" is an internal Jira identifier, but the name visible to Jira users is "Control Panel".
we can see that the component in Jira has been imported as an element of type "Component".
the associations between a component and the issues were imported as "allocates" relationship (in the case of requirements).
now we see an example of inferred information.
in this case these requirements are refinements of other requirements, which are already explicitly linked to this component.
by our model, there is an inference rule that requirements wchi are refinements are also allocated in the same component.
in this way, we have a richer view on the participation of any component in the system design.
Let's show the competence questions.
We have two groups of competence questions:
"Basic" questions and "traceability gaps" questions.
The items and links lists that we saw above contain the answers for the first two basic questions.
Which are questions that aim to retrieve the objects and their classifications, as well as relationships between the objects.
all these items are the listings we saw before.
in the basic questions group, we expect to find items that match the question.
No items are listed if not available in the original repository with this classification.
In case of any absence, it has to be analyzed by the project traceability responsibles.
the second group of competence questions is related to traceability gaps.
Different from the basic group, the expectation is not to find items that match the question.
It is up to the team to review whether the identified gaps are really a problem.
as an example, question CQ13 asks what are the requirements that are not allocated to any component.
In this case, we found requirements that are not allocated to any component, not even an inferred allocation.
It's up to the team to decide if this is an issue for project traceability.
ARCADE's intention is not to replace safety assurance specialists but to support their work by showing classified and filtered information.
it is also important to emphasize that ARCADE is not a modeling tool, nor it stores any data.
The team must fix any incorrectly classified or missing information.
All data is in the original repository, in our case Jira.
In this way, anyone consulting the project repository, or using the ARCADE, may deal with the correct and updated information.
ARCADE was designed to be easily extended with new competence questions, according to specific needs of the projects.
By using semantic web and description logic technologies, the extension of the Safety Assurance Information model and internal ontology is straightforward.
Let's demonstrate the consistency analysis.
when ARCADE finds no inconsistencies in the data loaded, the ontology is indicated as consistent.
Let's see how ARCADE handles some inconsistencies.
Here we have another example project on the domain of analgesic infusion pumps. Project data contains inconsistencies inside Jira, let's load it now.
Please notice that loading of data with inconsistencies can take a while due to the computation of the explanations.
after loading the data, there is information about whether the consistency is true or false.
if the consistency is false, explanations are computed to show which data items are in conflict with the model
Let's see these explanations, the items are still listed and below we have the verification for inconsistencies.
Here are listed the explanations, with a separation to show which items or links are involved, and which rules are impacted.
let's see the first explanation. We have the item "GPCA-7" which has a classification as Hazard, and at the same time the item is marked as a mitigator of item "GPCA-9".
however, by our rules, if a given object mitigates another, that object is a "safety requirement", and also by our rules we cannot have the same object being marked as a "requirement" and as a "hazard".
So in this case we have an inconsistency. we have a hazard that is mitigating some other object.
Another problem in the data is related to the item "GPCA-1", which is classified as a requirement. Item "GPCA-15" is marked as a refinement of "GPCA-1", but item "GPCA-15" is also classified as a "Design Definition".
However, if any object refines or is refined by a requirement, that object is also a requirement.
Similarly, there is a rule stating that items can not be at same time classified as a requirement and as a design definition.
These are two examples of inconsistencies that can be found and highlighted by ARCADE to support teams.
As said before, ARCADE does not make any decision about corrections.
Such decision is up to the team, which will fix items with a wrong classification.
Let's go to Jira, correct this information and reload the GPCA project in our system.
First let's see issue "GPCA-15", which should have been classified as a requirement that refines the requirement "GPCA-1" but ended up being incorrectly marked as a "design definition".
let's change the issue type, and then redo the loading of data in ARCADE.
Another problem is related to the issue "GPCA-7", which is a hazard and there is a link to mitigated to requirement "GPCA-9".
It seems that there was am inversion of the relationship.
Instead of being linked as "is mitigates by", it was linked "mitigates".
let's remove the wrong relationship and redo it correctly. So now let's select "is mitigated by" item GPCA-9, which is the correct item here.
let's now run again the data reload and see if the problems are solved. Just go to "Load project data" and then Load the project from Jira system again.
The reload is finished.
we can see that the consistency is true now and there are no more inconsistencies in the GPCA project.
let's see the items.
"GPCA-1" has a refinement to "GPCA-15", and "GPCA-15" is being classified as a requirement.
regarding the item "GPCA-7", now it has the correct direction of the mitigation relationship.
let's check the generation of fragments of safety assurance cases.
let's use the Open PCA project that is already loaded.
Two argumentation patterns selected from the literature are implemented: The Functional Decomposition Pattern the Hazard Avoidance Pattern.
In the functional decomposition pattern, the skeleton of the argumentation is formed by the requirements and their refinements.
in the hazard avoidance pattern, the argumentation is formed by the hazards, their refinements and the requirements that mitigate them.
In this version of ARCADE, fragments are generated in GSN notation and in SVG format.
Then here we can see the central part of the argument.
The GSN notation has a visual syntax and it is the most used notation in academia and industry, according to several studies.
It is straightforward to extend the framework to generate fragments in other patterns, formats or notations, depending on the specific needs of a team or an organization.
Let's show the other pattern, the hazard avoidance.
Both patterns are perspectives that complement each other and can be built on top of the same data.
the manual construction of both perspectives would be quite laborious.
the automated generation provides a preliminary view of the assurance cases effortlessly.
Here we conclude the framework presentation.
ARCADE aims to support teams to manage safety assurance information together with regular project information.
This integrated management allows thorough analysis of data and automatic generation of artifacts focused on certification, such as assurance cases.
In case of any question, please get in touch with our research team.
Thank you for your attention and participation!