Hello, welcome to the short training 1.2
this video provides an overview of issue tracking systems (IST) and
how these systems can be adapted to manage custom issues and custom relationships
we introduce some general concepts, describe basic usage and show how
these tools serve you to search and filter information related to project management
an IST is a software system for managing the lifecycle of a set of issues.
issues can represent a lot of different information related to a software project
these systems are widely adopted as a collaborative project management tool,
and they can record different kinds of information,
an IST can also be used as a repository of project's knowledge
Issue tracking normally are part of
ALM tools, which are used to manage the entire lifecycle of a product
in many cases, teams and organizations may use only
the issue tracking system as the management tool
Issue is the unit of work registered for management purposes
In the remainder of this video, we will use the term "item" to refer to an "issue"
Issues can represent a variety of information that a team decides to track:
bugs, change requests, tasks, etc.
the Atlassian Jira tool has predefined types of
issues that cover the basic needs of a software development project
an issue link is a bi-directional association that creates an
relationship between two issues
the Atlassian Jira tool has pre-defined link types focused on basic issue management
and it provides a type of link without semantics for free use ("relates to")
in the figure, we see an example of an issue within the Jira tool
the data fields are common and found in other tracking tools
for example, each issue
has a unique identifier that does not change throughout the lifecycle and does not repeat itself
in addition to pre-defined (built-in) issue types, issue link types and fields,
some tools allow you to create custom elements
for example, the "Description" field is pre-defined in Jira, while the "Justification" is a
custom field based on the SAIM model (that we discussed in the previous training)
the use of these custom fields allows you to associate more precise semantics
to the data filled in the issue
another example is the type of
issue "Story", which is already pre-defined in Jira and can be used to represent "Requirements"
however, the representation of "Hazards"
of the SAIM model doesn't fit properly with any of the pre-defined types,
so we set up an issue type called "Hazard" for a more accurate representation
and finally, in a similar way,
we created the custom issue link types to represent the SAIM model relationships
in the figure, the issue "GPCA-10" is a "Requirement" that has a mitigation link with two "Hazards"
these tools also bring a series of features for searching and filtering information,
including the creation of queries or advanced filters (we will see an example later in this video)
we customize an instance of Jira to incorporate the semantics of the SAIM model,
four specific types of issues were created while we reused others,
such as the issue type "Story" that we use to represent the requirements,
we also customized fields to represent the "Assumptions" and "Justifications" associated with issues
and, finally, we customized specific issue link types for the semantics
of the SAIM model, as shown in the table
let's now make a quick presentation of the custom Jira instance
This is the home page of Jira, displaying the issues of a project
the project is named OpenPCA
it is related to the exemplo we discussed in previous training
Each project in Jira has some
different views/perspectives over the set of issues
this one is the backlog view, that lists all the issues that are open,
and there is a view where I can see all the issues together:
the "All Issues" view
There are a series of filtering and data organization options, for example, I can
sort by unique identifier, sort by summary, sort by labels
In this example shown,  the "Stories" are mapped as "Requirements" and the
stories that have the label "safety" are mapped as "Safety Requirements"
we can also have a view sorted by Components,
we can also have a view sorted by issue types, for example,
the "Context" issues appear first, then "Design Definition", "Hazards", and "Stories"
Let's open one of these stories
This is the display of a Story, it contains a description. This requirement has no
rationale associated with it, but is related to other issues by the "is refined by"
relationship, i.e. the issues "12", "11", and "55" are refinements of the issue "8"
Apart from browsing through the issues, I may search for specific information using text search
for example, any issue containing "minimum" intervals
I found the story "24", which represents the minimum time between doses of analgesics
requested by patients, the issue has a description and there is a justification associated
which explains why this requirement is important for the design of the system
and for each issue there are the related links, this requirement "24"
mitigates the Hazard "31" and refines the requirement "22", which is a high-level requirement,
let's open Hazard "31". We see the description of the Hazard,
here we see information on which are the requirements in the system design that
can lead to this "Hazard" , i.e., that cause this Harzard,
as we showed before, the requirement "24" is mitigating this hazard
Also, there is the pre-defined "relates to" relationship, that we reuse to associate "Contexts" to other issues,
this relationship has no semantics in Jira,
so it was given a semantics to be the "contextualizes" relationship,
so we skip the creation of a new custom relationship
This is a "Context" issue, we have an attachment that is a Hazard Analysis
associated with the design, and there is another attachment that is a "Source" that documents this "Context"
this "Context" is related to a series of "Hazards", as a result
of the hazard analysis that was carried out
so these are the basic features that every good IST brings for users,
In order to browse this repository of knowledge, the collection of issues that are registered in the system
you can also apply some filters, for example,
I want to filter the issue list by Hazards,
so you already have a filter in the IST, which lists only the issues that are of the Hazards type
If I want to filter all the Design Definition issues,
there is also a filter
and also there is a series of other fields that can be used as filter criteria
this was the walkthrough in the custom Atlassian Jira tool for the SAIM model
We described how an IST can support the management of
assurance information in an integrated way with the other project information
IST has features that support their use as a knowledge repository,
such as search and filtering, data exporting,
and customization,
which allows users to manage information with richer semantics.
Thank you for your attention.