Hello, welcome to the short training 1.3!
this video introduces the basics about safety assurance cases using the GSN notation.
let's introduce some general concepts about assurance cases, introduce the GSN notation, and show an example of a safety assurance case.
An assurance case represents a reasoned and compelling argument that a service, system or organization will operate as intended for a given application in a given environment
In other words, the assurance case makes a solid argument based on evidence that the system operates and complies with requirements specifications.
safety assurance cases, in particular, focus on demonstrating that a given system is acceptably safe to operate in a given context.
arguments are structured as a series of claims that state an overall claim.
for example, in the design of a critical system the main claim is that the system is acceptably safe to operate.
the claims are refined into supporting claims, and these supporting claims provide rationales to explain requirements and design decisions.
examples of claims are requirements, hazards, design definitions or any aspect of the system design that needs to be adequately satisfied or mitigated.
at some point in the argumentation, claims are not further refined and are linked to pieces of evidence that support them.
the set of evidence is formed by artifacts produced throughout the development process
The Goal Structuring Notation (G.S.N.) is a visual notation for building the arguments of assurance cases.
By using GSN, it is possible to explicitly document the entire hierarchy of claims and evidence that structure the argument in favor of a system.
the notation provides a semantics for constructing arguments.
Claims are called "Goals", supporting arguments can be "Strategies", "Assumption" or "Justifications", and items of evidence are ultimately "Solutions", contextual information is mapped to elements of type "Context".
the G.S.N. main elements follow the visual notation depicted on the left.
in the figure on the right, there is a partial example of an assurance case.
"Goals" represent something to be achieved, for example a requirement to be implemented, or a hazard to be adequately mitigated
the "Goals" comprise the central structure of the argumentation.
"Strategies" represent explanations that clarify how the high-level goal connects to supporting goals.
for example in the figure, the strategy for dealing with hazard analysis is to argue separately about product and process aspects.
throughout the argumentation, it may be necessary to contextualize information, the "Context" element is used to represent this.
in the example of the image, a requirements specification is used as "Context".
finally, in the bottom of the argument it is expected to have items of evidence, called "Solutions".
these solutions point to artifacts generated during the development of the system.
if an Goal is not refined into other Goals or linked to Solutions, we say that the Goal is undeveloped, which is expected in the early phases of the project life cycle.
the GSN notation also defines two types of elements to represent rationales: the "Justifications" and the "Assumptions".
the links allowed between GSN elements are the link "Supported By" and the link "In Context Of".
in the previous slide, it is demonstrated the use of the "supported by" link that interconnects goals.
The "in context of" link serves to associate the main arguments to contextual or rationale information such as justifications and assumptions.
let's present an example of a assurance case specified in GSN, which is based in the same design model from the illustrative example of training 1.1.
the design refers to a patient-controlled analgesic infusion pump, the part of the design that we deal with in this example involves mitigating the hazard of battery exhaustion.
the figure shows the modeling based on the Safety Assurance Information Model presented on training 1.1.
Let's show how this information can be organized into an argument using GSN.
the arguments are built based on the design information, in this part of the argument the focus is on the hazard of battery exhaustion.
the mitigation of this hazard is mapped as a high-level goal in the argument.
Throughout this example, we are highlighting the referred part of the model on the left and on the right how the element is mapped into the GSN argument.
the argument then starts with a high-level hazard that was selected: battery exhaustion.
in order to contextualize the hazard category to which this "battery exhaustion" belongs, we mapped the high-level under-infusion hazard as a "Context" element.
Continuing in the argument development, the requirement "caregiver notification" mitigates the hazard of battery drain.
Hence, the requirement is mapped as a Goal and a "supported by" link is created between hazard and requirement.
in turn, the assumption "Sufficient time", that provides an explanation for the notification requirement, is mapped as an Assumption and connected through the link "In Context Of".
the allocation of the requirement is also an important contextual information.
so the notification module is mapped as a "Context" element.
there is also an "exhaustion notification" requirement that refines the "caregiver notification" requirement, which is mapped as a "Goal" and linked by a "Supported By".
and finally, the two sources that document the "exhaustion notification" requirement are mapped as "Solutions", thus representing supporting evidence to the argument.
it is important to emphasize that this is one of the valid alternatives for mapping the design of this project to an argument in GSN, but it is not the only one.
the mitigation of the hazard can be argued from other perspectives, since there are a variety of argumentation patterns.
All in all, whatever the pattern of argumentation is, the information used is the same and is originated in the project development artifacts.
we completed this short training aimed to leverage some concepts about assurance cases.
they are built based on project information, also requiring information on rationales and safety assurance.
there is no direct mapping of project data to GSN elements, as the same project items can be mapped differently depending on the argumentation pattern adopted.
Thanks for your attention and participation!