Hello, welcome this is short training 2.1.
Let's introduce the ARCADE Framework
The main purpose of the Arcade Framework is the integrated management of safety assurance information
together with with regular project development information
The figure illustrates the Framework application context,
where project teams and safety analysis teams use the same
project management tools to store and retrieve information on the development lifecycle of a system
safety analysis teams, in particular,
need to produce artifacts for certification, such as safety assurance cases
it is a task that can be complex in case project data does not conform
to a defined underlying information metamodel; and also when data related to safety assurance
is disconnected from regular project data
the ARCADE Framework provides support for the development process and preparation
for certification through a series of features
the ARCADE promotes integrated management of safety assurance data
using common project management tools
such as issue tracking systems or ALMs (Application Lifecycle Management)
ARCADE supports the automated extraction of project data to perform a variety
of analyzes , so that we could integrate it more easily into the a development pipeline
ARCADE also performs data consistency analysis according
to the Safety Assurance Information Model (SAIM) along with
other rules that are implemented in the internal ontology
ARCADE framework supports knowledge discovery by generating
reports to classify and cross-reference explicit and implicit information extracted from the tools
We call "implicit" information those which are inferred from
the explicit information extracted from project management tool.
this contributes to a better knowledge discovery within the project's repository
Finally, ARCADE automatically generates fragments of
safety assurance cases based on a couple of argumentation patterns
the aim is to provide safety teams with multiple perspectives over the same data
without the need to manually built
different safety assurance cases in a visual modeling tool
the scenarios of use that ARCADE helps to automate are:
reviewing project and assurance information,
exploring this information with a focus on knowledge discovery,
and producing safety assurance case reports for a project by
reusing the automatically generated fragments
the framework workflow starts with the extraction of
information from the project management tool
In this version of the framework, we connect ARCADE with a issue tracking system (Jira) that contains
issues, fields within those issues, and links between issues
this issue data is extracted by ARCADE and fed into
an internal model based on the schema of the SAIM model
this internal model is loaded into the internal ontology of ARCADE, which performs the following actions:
verification of data consistency
if inconsistencies are found, explanations are computed to highlight the
item of project data that have deviations, also highlighting which rules were violated
if the data is consistent, implicit classifications will be inferred,
and the inferred data is fed back
into the ontology, thus leaving the internal model with a mix of provided and inferred data
on top of this combined data, queries are performed to retrieve
information according to a set of competence questions implemented in the framework
later on this video, some of these questions implemented in ARCADE will be shown
"competence question" is a term from the ontology domain and represents
a relevant question that a knowledge-based system needs to respond to users
in ARCADE, the competence questions were devise to support the work
of the development and safety teams,
focusing on extracting information about the project's traceability
finally, also on top of the same combined data, it is carried out
some queries and the construction of arguments in GSN notation
we use the term "fragment" to denote that the arguments generated are not complete
assurance cases reports, but rather a partial view that follows a pattern of argumentation from the literature
we will present ARCADE, the version that presented in this video is an
instance of the framework deployed at a web address,
which connects with a project management tool that we chose for initial integration
this Atlassian Jira was customized
to adopt the SAIM model, it is the same show in training 1.2
This is the main screen of the ARCADE tool, there are some pages with more detailed information
about how the framework operates, how to adapt it for use, and a breakdown
of the features and design decisions related to its development
let's use the ARCADE tool
of the tool starts with loading the ontology specification,
which contains the rules and axioms verified by ARCADE
the tool already leaves this specification preloaded,
the specification can be seen in these links at the beginning of the home page
if you want to reset the ontology, just click on "Reset" and the ontology is reloaded in the system
the project data extraction is available for three projects hosted in the Jira instance
the Open PCA project has already been explored in the first part of this evaluation,
and in this second part we are going to explore the DRONE project
when requesting to load a project, ARCADE connects to the issue tracking system through
the external access API, and retrieves the project data in the proprietary format defined by Jira
this data is transformed to the internal SAIM model
and then fed into the internal ontology
Let's load Open PCA Project data directly from Jira,
the process may take a few seconds, because after transferring data between servers
and transforming the data, ARCADE triggers the routines for consistency analysis,
classification of information and generation of safety assurance cases
if the data loading went without problems, a success message is shown
some technical data is shown in the "details" section
the number of items that were recovered,
this number includes issues, components and custom fields,
anything that is an element of the SAIM model, for example, assumptions and justifications
number of relationships between items
quantity of attributes related to these items
regarding the inferred data, the details show new inferred classifications for
items and new inferred relationships
Let's show how ARCADE supports knowledge discovery using the Open PCA project
the project is hosted in Jira and was automatically loaded,
it contains 94 objects from the SAIM model
these objects comprise issues, components and custom fields
e.g. issue
OPENPCA-71 is registered in Jira as a "Story" and was then mapped as a "Requirement"
some fields were extracted to fill the attributes of SAIM model:
name, description, status, creation date,
update date and a URL in case you want to access the same issue in the original tool
some elements of the SAIM model, which were mapped as custom fields in Jira,
are imported as separate objects, such as assumptions and justifications
and, finally, relationships with other issues were also extracted
in the example show, the requirement is refined by three other requirements
This view differs from the view provided by the
Jira tool, as the semantics of the SAIM model was applied
Another example is "Component10026"
"Component10026" is an internal Jira identifier,
but the name visible to Jira users is "Control Panel"
we can see that
the component in Jira has been imported as an element of type "Component" of SAIM model
the associations between a component and the issues were
imported as "allocates" relationship (in the case of requirements)
now we see an example of inferred information, in this case these requirements are
refinements of other requirements, which are already explicitly linked to this component
by our model, there is an inference rule that the requirements that
are refinements are also allocated in the same component
this way, we have a richer view on the participation of any component in the system design
Let's show the competence questions
We have two groups of competence questions:
"Basic" questions and "traceability gaps" questions
that items listing that we saw above are the answer for the first two basic questions,
which are questions that seek to rescue which are the objects and their classifications,
and which are the relationships between the objects
all these items can be found in the view above
in the basic questions group,
the expectation is to found items that match the question
if no items are returned, it means there is not yet in the original repository any
project items with this classification, and this absence needs
to be analyzed by whoever is in charge of the project traceability review
the second group of competence questions is related to traceability gaps,
different from the basic group, the expectation is not to find items that match the question
It is up to the team to review whether the identified gaps are really a problem
as illustration, question CQ13 asks what are
the requirements that are not allocated to any component
in this case, we found requirements that are not allocated to any component,
not even an inferred allocation
So whether or not this is an issue for project traceability
is up to the team to decide
ARCADE's intention is not to replace safety assurance specialists
but to support their work by showing classified and filtered information
it is also important to emphasize that ARCADE is not
a modeling tool, nor does it store its own data
if any information is classified incorrectly or is missing, the team must correct
the data directly in the original repository, in our case the Jira issue system
in this way, who later consult the project repository, or use the ARCADE,
you will work with the correct, updated information
the design of ARCADE was planned to be easily extended with new
competence questions, according to specific needs of the projects
By using semantic web and description logic technologies,
the extension of the SAIM model and internal ontology is straightforward
Let's demonstrate the consistency analysis
when ARCADE finds no inconsistencies in the data loaded,
the ontology is indicated as consistent
Let's demonstrate how ARCADE handles a set of data that contains inconsistencies
we have an example project, also based on the domain of analgesic infusion pumps,
this data contains inconsistencies inside Jira and we are going to load it now
the video has been paused because the loading of data with inconsistencies can take
a while, due to the computation of the explanations
after loading the data, there is information about whether the consistency is true or false. if the
consistency is false, explanations are computed to show the user which
data items are in conflict with the SAIM model
let's see these explanations, the items are still listed
and below we have the verification for inconsistencies
There are explanations shown, with a separation to show which
items or links are involved, and which rules are impacted
let's explain the first explanation. We have the item "GPCA-7" which has a
classification as Hazard, and at the same time the item is marked as a mitigator of item "GPCA-9"
however, by our rules, if a given object mitigates another,
that object is a "safety requirement", and also by our rules we cannot
have the same object being marked as a "requirement" and as a "hazard", so in this
case we have an inconsistency. we have a hazard that is mitigating some other object.
another problem we also have in the data is related to
the item "GPCA-1" which is classified as a requirement, item "GPCA-15" is marked as
a refinement of "GPCA-1", but item "GPCA-15" is also classified as a "Design Definition"
in that case, we have a rule that if any object refines
or is refined by a requirement, that object is also a requirement.
similarly, there is a rule stating that items can not be
at same time classified as a requirement and as a design definition
These are two examples of inconsistencies that can be found
and highlighted by ARCADE to help the teams
As we pointed out earlier, ARCADE does not make any decision about what the correction should be:
this decision is up to the team, which will decide which of the items has the wrong classification.
Let's go to Jira, correct this information and reload the GPCA project in our system
so first let's go to issue "GPCA-15", which in reality should have been classified as an requirement,
that refines the requirement "GPCA-1". But it ended up being incorrectly marked as a "design definition"
let's change the issue type, and then redo the loading of data in ARCADE
another problem is related to the issue "GPCA-7", which is a hazard
and there is a link to mitigated to requirement "GPCA-9". It seems that there was am inversion of the relationship,
instead of being linked as "is mitigates by ", it was linked "mitigates"
let's remove the wrong relationship and redo it correctly
let's now run again the data reload and see if the problems are solved
let's see
the reload is finished
we can see that the consistency is true now,
there are no more inconsistencies in the GPCA project
let's see the items
"GPCA-1" has a refinement to "GPCA-15", and "GPCA-15" is being classified as a requirement
regarding the item "GPCA-7",
now it has the correct direction of the mitigation relationship
let's see the generation of fragments of safety assurance cases,
let's use the Open PCA project that is already loaded
so at the bottom of the home page, we have the arguments
there are two argumentation patterns implemented that we selected from the literature
one pattern is the Functional Decomposition Pattern, and the second is the Hazard Avoidance Pattern
in the functional decomposition pattern,
the skeleton of the argumentation is formed by the requirements and their refinements
in the hazard avoidance pattern, the argumentation is formed by the hazards,
their refinements and the requirements that mitigate them
In this version of ARCADE, fragments are generated in GSN notation and in svg format
we show here the central part of the argument
the GSN notation has a visual syntax and it is
the most used notation in academia and industry, according to several studies
It is straightforward to extend the framework to generate fragments in other patterns, formats or notations,
depending on the specific needs of a team or an organization
Let's show the other pattern, the hazard avoidance
Both patterns are perspectives that complement each other and can be built on top of the same data
the manual construction of both perspectives would be quite laborious,
the automated generation provides a preliminary view of the assurance cases effortlessly
We concluded the framework presentation.
ARCADE aims to support teams to manage safety assurance information
together with regular project information
This integrated management allows thorough analysis of data and automatic generation
of artifacts focused on certification, such as assurance cases
Any questions, please get in touch.
thank you for your attention