Hi, welcome to the short training 1.1
this video presents the Safety Assurance Information Model
we will start by reviewing some general concepts, then we present the information model,
and finally we present an illustrative example of the use of the model
the first concept is "Safety", which refers to the absence
of unacceptable risks in the design and implementation of a critical system
"Safety assurance" refers to the systematic and planned actions, activities and processes
that are necessary to provide adequate confidence that the product,
service or system under development has achieved an acceptable level of safety
"Information model" refers to a representation of concepts and
relationships, constraints, rules and operations that specify the semantics
for a given set of data within an application domain
What is the Safety Assurance Information Model (SAIM)? The purpose of this information model
is to represent critical system project development information
The model focuses on information that is relevant to
quality assessment and safety assurance activities, especially
Assurance Case development activities. The SAIM model combines three perspectives:
i) The model requirements traceability reference model by Ramesh & Jarke
ii) the requirements metamodel focused on security requirements by Vilela
and iii) the Assurance Cases specification model based on GSN notation
We provide links to these works in the video description
This is the SAIM metamodel
the main concept is "Object". which refer to any type of input or output
of the system development process at the level of granularity that the team
decided to manage them. "Sources" are any type of
external artifact that is linked to "Objects" but which are not managed within the tools
the "documents" relationship can link a "Source" to an "Object" that it documents
the other types of elements that appear in the
SAIM model are recurring concepts in the modeling of safety requirements
"Requirements" represent the expected conditions or capabilities that the system must satisfy
"Hazards" represent system states that can lead to accidents or cause harm
"Safety Requirements" is a subtype of "Requirement" that is related to safety aspects
the "mitigates" relationship links the "Safety Requirement" to the "Hazards"
they address
"Definition Design" is a design decision that
specifies or constrains parts of the system or some component
the "realizes" relationship links a "Design Definition" to the "Requirements" it realizes
"Components" are units of architecture, modules or system code at any
level the team has decided to track. There are two relationships linked to "Components"
the "allocates" relationship links a "Component" to the "Requirements" that are assigned to it
and the "implements" relationship links a
"Component" to "Design Definitions" that are implemented by it
"Causes" is any "Object" that produces some kind of "Hazard" as its effect
e.g., a new "Requirement" or "Design Definition" may cause a
"Hazard" so it should be mapped also as a "Cause"
the "causes" relationship links any "Object" to "Hazards" that are caused by it
"Contexts" are environmental or operational conditions that are relevant to safety
"Objects" that contextualizes others are represented
by the "contextualizes" relationship
"Rationale" is an explanation that provides
additional information for some "Object". One of the types is "Justification", that is
an explanation about a decision related to requirements, design or hazards
"Assumption" is an explanation that assumes a common
domain situation held true by stakeholders
"Strategy" is an explanation of mitigation approaches or related argumentation
"Rationales" can be linked to other "Objects" through the "explains" relationship
the SAIM model also includes attributes for the "Objects"
these attributes represent data information
commonly stored in management tools
and are helpful to leverage the analysis of project data
automatically extracted from project management tools
we will now present an illustrative example of how the SAIM model can be used to
represent data from a critical system project. the example is related to the design of a
patient-controlled analgesic infusion pump used within a clinical setting
we will discuss the part of the design related to the notification of caregivers
that is triggered in the event of detecting of imminent battery exhaustion
the diagram in the figure shows the model based in SAIM, which will be discussed step by step now
Hazard of battery exhaustion is part of a group of hazards related to under-infusion
it occurs when the patient receives less analgesic doses than prescribed
in the example, the hazard of under-infusion is represented as the object "H1"
the hazard of battery exhaustion is represented as object "H2" that refines the hazard "H1"
In order to mitigate the hazard "H2",
the safety requirement "R1" concerning notification function for caregivers has been defined,
assumption "A1" presents a rationale for requirement "R1", the assumption
provides an explanation regarding the advance required in triggering the notification
requirement "R1" is allocated in component "Comp3" concerning the notification module
all these information items can be modeled using the SAIM
Continuing, requirement "R1" is refined into a low-level requirement called "R4"
requirement "R4" details how the exhaustion notification will work by specifying
the criteria for triggering the notification. Finally requirement "R4" has evidence
associated with its implementation and testing. In this case, they are external artifacts mapped as "Sources"
we concluded the quick training. the objective was to show how
safety information can be managed together with other project information
the SAIM model serves as a guide for the organization of project information
the model was planned to be lean and be extended according to the particularities of each project
Thank you for your attention